你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院
welcome to pwn College
我是Yan，今天要讨论的是程序交互方式
I'm Yan and today we're going to be talking about interacting with programs
这个模块全是关于程序交互方式的
this module is all about interacting with programs
通过各种渠道和方式，输入数据
sending them input in various ways through various channels
控制它们运行的环境等等
controlling the environment they run in etc etc and
这个视频将是一个速成班
this video is going to be a crash course in
我希望这些信息能用来复盘
information that I hope will be a review
提醒你命令行的用法
to remind you how the command line works
以及如何启动程序，等等
and how programs are invoked and etc
好了，我们开始吧
all right let's dive in
希望你们都
so you've hopefully all ran at some point in your lives
在linux命令行中执行过helloworld程序
a Hello World program from the Linux command line
执行./helloworld
you do ./helloworld
会输出Hello World然后退出
prints out Hello World and exit
那么这么做时，到底发生了什么
so what happens under the hood when you do that
Linux做了很多事
well Linux does a bunch of stuff
它提供了启动程序所需的环境
it facilitates the launching of your program
这会在以后的视频中学习
which we will learn about in future videos
它能恰当地调节处理
it figures out how to properly mediate interaction
程序创建的进程与执行环境的关系
between the process that your program creates and the environment it runs in
等等
and so on
Linux很重要
Linux is relevant
因为，它是这门课用的
because this is what we're using for this class
而且，它可能是世上最流行的操作系统
it's probably the most popular operating system in the world
鉴于，路由器里运行的它
when you factor in the routers it runs in
Android手机等都是由它赋能的
the Android phones etc etc that it powers
所以这门课我们将用Linux
so in this class we'll use Linux
探讨各种网络安全概念
to explore these various cybersecurity concepts
Linux的主要交互方式是命令行
and your main interaction with Linux will be the command line
所以我们开启一个命令行快速入门之旅
so we're going to do a quick command line crash refresher
什么是命令行
what is the command line
命令行也被称为shell
well the command line also known as the shell
它是计算机的一个强大接口
it's powerful interface to use a computer
通常你会输入命令
generally you type in commands
shell会执行这些命令并显示结果
and the shell execute those commands and shows you results
一条典型的命令，包含一个shell内置功能
a typical command contains either a built in functionality of the shell
或程序名，即计算机上有的程序
or a program name a program that exists on your computer
然后是空格分隔的程序参数
and then argument to that program separated by spaces
这里我执行了cat flag
here I do a cat flag
shell由此得知
what happens is the shell sees
我想用flag参数，执行cat
I want to run the cat program with a flag argument
shell启动cat程序
it invokes the cat program
启动结果会创建一个进程
the process that results from that invocation
等一下，我改一下这张幻灯片
hold on a second let me fix this slide 1 sec
好了，原来多打了 /
there we go I add a slashes where there shouldn't have been slashes
很抱歉
sorry about that
启动cat flag时所创建的进程
what happened is the process that results from the invocation of cat flag
会读取它的第一个参数，即flag
reads its first argument which is flag
打开这个文件
opens that file
然后将它输出到标准输出，即终端屏幕
and prints it to standard output to the output of the terminal
这就是cat的用途
that's what cat is designed to do
它能读出文件内容
it reads out files
如果你从来没用过cat，该怎么知道如何使用
so how would you know what cat is supposed to do if you had never run cat before
你应该知道cat的用法
well you should really know what cat does
这是一个很基础的东西
that's a very basic thing
如果你不知道
if you don't
有很多途径可以学
there's a number of ways to get familiar
一是，你可以玩一个叫Bandit的wargame
one is you can run through a war game called Bandit
它肯定能让你十分熟悉命令行，和一些其它概念
that familiarizes you forcefully with the command line and some other concepts
你可以在网上搜索教程
you can search online for tutorials
或者你最该做的是
or really what you should be doing is
使用Linux系统上的优秀文档
using the awesome documentation that comes on Linux systems
man 手册
the man pages
执行 man cat
you do man cat
你会得到这个十分有用的cat帮助文档
you get this very helpful help output about cat
对于我提过几次的shell内置命令
for shell builtins I mentioned this several times
例如用于更改目录的cd
for example cd to change directories
你可以执行 help cd
you can do help cd
来了解它的用途
to read about what they do
如果你真的被难住了，可以问
or if you really get stumped ask
可以在pwn.college的Discord频到上问我们
ask us on the pwn College Discord
我们总是很乐意提供一定帮助
we're always happy to help to an extent
这是在学习这门课之前应该知道的
this is something that you should know before tackling the course in general
好的
all right
我提到了进程
so I mentioned processes
我们快速地带一下
we're going to skim over this real quick
因为这是本模块之后视频的主题
because it will be the subject of future videos in this module
进程是一个运行中的程序
a process is a running program
程序实际上就是你电脑上的一个文件
and a program really is a file on your computer
cat是我电脑上的一个可执行文件
cat exists somewhere in an executable file on my computer
我们之后会讨论这个
we'll talk about that in a sec
这些可执行文件位于文件系统中
and these executables files live in a file system
web浏览器等电脑里所有的文件都在文件系统中
so your web browser every file in your computer lives in a file system
我们将在以后的视频中深入介绍可执行文件本身
and we will cover the executables themselves in depth in a bit in future videos
现在我们讨论一下文件系统
for now let's talk about the file system
它是文件的居所
which is where files live
你可能有使用Windows的经验
you might have experience with Windows
大多数人都有
most people do
在Windows系统中，有一个C盘
in Windows you have a C drive
如果你还有其它盘
if you have additional drives
或者像以前我们还用cd光驱
or back in the day when we had cd ROM drives
你可能有D盘，E盘等等
you might have a D drive an E drive etc etc
插入一个闪存
you plug in a flash drive
它会变成F盘之类的
it becomes an F drive whatever
如果你接触过软盘
if you ever interacted with a floppy disk
A盘和B盘就是为它准备的
that's where A and B were from
不管怎样，Windows把所有这些文件系统都分开
anyways Windows has all of these file systems separated out
锚定在不同的字母上
anchored into different letters
Linux不是这样的
Linux is not like that
Linux提供统一的文件系统视图
Linux presents a unified file system view
它锚定在 /
it is anchored at slash
也叫root
also pronounced root
文件系统树的根
the root of the file system tree
这个名字有点容易混淆
that's a little bit of a confusing nomenclature
因为root也用于其他一些概念
because root is used for some other concepts
但这没办法
but let's I mean there's no way around it
它锚定在/或称为root
it's anchored at slash or root otherwise known
在这棵树下有很多目录
and there's a bunch of directories in a crazy tree under that
幻灯片上有些常见的
here are some common ones on the slides
例如
for example
/user，大家都这么读
/user that's how everyone pronounces it
但它实际上不是指用户
but it's not actually user
它代表Unix System Resource
it stands for Unix System Resource
这里存储着Unix系统资源
that's where your Unix systems resources are stored
包含了，ppt上写的是全部，但不是全部
and contains like well I say all on the slide but not all
它包含许多系统文件
it contains many many many system files
比如/usr/bin下的可执行文件
such as executable files in user bin
如果你现在看看你的系统
if you look on your system right now
剧透一下，这里放着cat
spoiler alert that's where cat lives
在/usr/lib里还有库
it has libraries in user lib
/usr/share下的程序共享资源
shared program resources in user share
/etc有你的系统配置
/etc has your system configuration
/var包含系统的日志和缓存
/var has logs and caches for the system
/home放着你的数据
/home is where all your data is
特别是，PWN学院的设施中
specifically in the pwn college infrastructure
在/home/ctf下，是给你的持久home目录
in home ctf is your persistent home directory
/proc，你可以看看
/proc you can go and look around and
里面有关于进程的，系统配置的信息
has information about processes about system configurations
在/proc中有很多好东西
a lot of good stuff in /proc
还可在/tmp中查看缓存数据
very interesting to dig around in the /tmp for temporary data storage
还有很多很多很多
and much much much much more
这是一个惯例约定
this is kind of the convention
实际上有一个Linux标准叫LSB
there is actually a Linux standard called the Linux Standard Base
它指定了典型Linux系统中必须存在的目录
that specifies what directories really have to be there in a typical Linux system
但Linux实际上是很可自定义的
but a Linux is actually very very very configurable
你可以自己创建一个Linux发行版
you could create a Linux distribution
例如，有些Linux发行版具有完全不同的文件系统布局
there are Linux distributions that have a completely different filesystem layout for example
但这个是Linux文件系统的典型组织结构
but this is kind of your typical organization of a Linux file system
我刚刚列举的所有东西
and all of the things I just named off
所有的这些文件和目录
all of those files and directories
目录保存文件。文件存储在目录中
directories hold files files are stored in directories
这应该是非常普遍的观点
this should really hopefully be very much of view
有趣的是
what is interesting is
每个进程在某种意义上运行在一个目录中
each process runs in some sense in a directory
每个进程都知道自己当前的工作目录
each process has a sense of what is my current working directory
默认从这个目录开始找文件之类的
the directory where by default I'll start looking for files stuff like that
shell只是个进程
your shell is just a process
一个命令解释器
your command interpreter
并且它知道自己的当前工作目录
and it has an understanding of its current working directory
你可以用pwd查看当前的工作目录
and you can actually view what the current working directory is with the pwd
内置的打印工作目录工具
built in print working directory
它通常会展示在这里，提醒你
it also usually shows in your prompt like here
最初，当前工作目录在这个波浪号
I start out current working directory is this tilde
这是主目录的简写
that's a shorthand for I am in my home directory
比如，如你执行pwd后所见，/home/yans
for example home yans as you can see from executing pwd
可以用ls，列出目录中的文件
you can list the files in the directory with ls
这是我主目录下的文件
so here's files in my home directory
我还可以移动到另一个目录
and I can move to another directory
用内置的cd，修改当前工作目录
change my current working directory with the cd built in
当我执行 cd /usr
and when I do cd /usr
当前工作目录变成了/usr
my current work directory becomes usr
我能用ls查看一下
I can list that
我可以进入到之前在主目录中看到的目录
I can go into this previous directory I'd seen in my home directory
/home/yans/flags
home yans flags
我能看到
I can see that
能看到有一个TOPSECRET文件
I can see that there's a topsecret file
我能用cat输出TOPSECRET文件
and I can cat out that topsecret file
很酷
pretty cool
目录可以保存文件和其他目录
directories hold files and other directories all right
我们来讨论一下path
let's talk about paths for a sec
在前面的例子中，我
in that previous example I was
我执行了cat /home/yans/flags
I did cat /home/yans/flags
但这很冗长
but that's very tedious
如果你总是从/开始
if you always have to start from slash
目录会变得很深，特别是在一些复杂系统
directories get pretty deep especially in a complex system
尤其是在做软件开发的时候
especially if you're doing software development
有模块和子模块，它们都
when you have modules and submodules and all of them are
所有的代码在不同的目录和子目录
all the source codes in different directories and subdirectories
总是写绝对路径将是一个噩梦
it's a nightmare to always type what is called an absolute path
它是以 / 开头的路径
a path that starts with slash
从文件系统树的最开头开始指定的路径
a path that refers to the very beginning of the file system tree
你不会想这么做的
you don't want to do that
这就是为什么我们发明了相对路径
and that's why we invented relative path
相对路径不以 / 开头
relative path don't start with a slash
它们是相对于当前工作目录的
and they are relative to the current working directory
所以前面讲的概念，每个进程的当前工作目录
so that previous concept talked about every process's current working directory
的真正用处是，在进程尝试访问相对路径时
where that's really used is when the process tries to access a relative path
该相对路径从当前工作目录开始
that relative path starts from that current working directory
这里，我当前的工作目录在/home/yans
here my current work directory is in home yans
我尝试cat TOPSECRET
I try to cat topsecret
/home/yans中没有TOPSECRET文件
there's no topsecret file in home yans
它在/home/yans/flags中
it's in home yans flags
如果我cd进flags，然后cat TOPSECRET
if I cd into flags and then cat topsecret
就输出来了
then it comes out
这些路径没有
these paths don't
以 / 开头的路径是绝对路径
the paths that do start with slash again are absolute paths
这三个不以斜杠开头的路径是相对路径
these are three paths that don't start with slash are relative paths
它们相对于当前工作目录
relative to the current working directory
我们仔细看看路径
let's take a closer look at paths
一条路径有几个不同的组件，可能的组件
specifically there are several different components of a path possible components
首先可能是开头的 /
first you might have that leading forward slash
这创建了一个绝对路径
that creates an absolute path
然后有一堆目录名
then you have a bunch of directory names
我们认为这样比较易懂
we just kind of assumed that this was obvious
/home表示home目录
slash home that is the home directory
/yans表示yans目录
slash yans the yans directory
每次一个目录后加上 / 表示
so every time I put a slash after a directory I signify
要查看这个目录的内部
hey let's look inside that directory right
我们要用这个目录内部的资源
we're referencing some resource inside the directory
路径中也可能有一个点
there's also a dot that can be in the path
点是一个特殊条目，基本上表示它自己
a dot is a special entry in a directory that basically signifies itself
我马上会解释为什么这很重要
and I'll explain why that is important in a second
基本上你能用 ./blah/blah
but basically you can do dot slash blah blah blah blah
它就和在你的当前工作目录 blah/blah 一样
and it's still your current directory slash something
你可以在路径内的任意位置用 .
you can do dot at any point inside the path
还能用 ..
or you can do a dot dot
这意味着退后一步
that means step back
往树上走，或者说向树根更近一步
step up the tree or closer to the anchor the root of the tree
进入包含当前目录的目录
step into the directory that contains my directory
当然，路径的末尾有一个文件名
and then of course at the end of the path you have a file name
通常是你的最终目的地
often your final destination
这些是访问同一个文件的不同方法
so these are different ways to access the same file
如果最初在/usr/bin
if you start out in user bin
我们能用TOPSECRET的绝对路径找到它
we can reference this topsecret file using its full path
也能用相对路径
we can do a relative walk basically
从/usr/bin出发的相对路径
a relative path from user bin
到../../home
to dot dot slash dot dot slash home
这2个../能带我们到根目录
and because this two dot dot slashes gets us into slash
第一个../把我们带到/usr
the first dot dot slash puts us into or puts us references slash user
第二个../把我们带到/
the second dot dot slash references slash
然后跟着home/yans/flags/TOPSECRET
and then we have home yans flags topsecret
还有这一长串也指的同一个文件
and then this all is also referencing the same file
看一下这个有趣的路径
so look this very interesting thing where
最开始指向当前目录
I started out referencing the current directory
但因为../等等
but because I did dot dot slash etc etc
最后又回到了老后面去了
I ended up way back up
一直回到root
all the way back to root
然后再到home/yans/等
and then into home yans etc
这实际上是一类被称为路径遍历的漏洞的起因
this is actually the source of a vulnerability class known as path traversal
通常在一个不够小心的程序中
oftentimes in an application that is not careful
有可能混入这些 ../../../等
it's possible to sneak in these dot dot slashes etc
获取应用程序不想让你拿到的文件
to get at files that the application doesn't want you to get at
但这要很后面才会讲
but that's looking way ahead
这不是我们这门课要深入研究的内容
and not actually something that we'll dig into in this course
但这是一个有趣的安全问题
but it's an interesting security thing to know
好了，这就是对路径的剖析
all right so this is the anatomy of a path
现在我们执行过cat 路径
now we did cat some path
但cat本身在哪里呢
but where is cat itself
cat是一个指向程序的相对路径吗
is cat a relative path to a program
如果是，那执行cat flags/TOPSECRET时
if so when we did cat Flags topSecret
当前目录下应该有一个cat文件
we would expect that there is a cat file in the current directory
但能看到，这里没有
but you can see there is not
如果你尝试用cat 输出它
and if you try to cat it out
它不存在，对吧
it doesn't exist right
事实证明
it turns out that
如果命令的第一个字符不是/
if the first word of a command has no forward slash characters
当然你可以用./cat
now of course you could do dot slash cat
尝试执行一个在当前目录中的cat
and try to execute a cat file in the local directory
你可以给一个绝对路径
you can give an absolute path
但如果命令的第一个字符不是/
but if the first word of the command has no forward slash characters
shell就会去找该程序
the shell will search for that program
或者找它的内置命令
or either it'll search its builtins stuff like cd
如cd之类的写入在shell解释器本身中的内置命令
and so on built in functionality programmed into the shell interpreter itself
或在path变量指定的目录里
or it'll search its file system through a set of directories specified in the path variable
寻找目标程序
for that program
path变量到底是什么
so what the heck is a path variable
一般的变量是什么
well what's a variable in general
这里我指的是环境变量
here I'm referring to environment variables
是一个在Linux和大多数操作系统中都有的概念
a concept in Linux and most operating systems actually
基本上是每个进程启动时都会收到的一些信息
where basically every process will start with some information handed to it
以后的视频会讨论，是怎么传给它，以及存在哪里
we'll talk later about how that information gets there where it's stored in future videos
现在可以认为是每个进程启动时都带有一组键值对
but for now consider that every process starts with a set of key value pairs
在它启动时
when it's launched
等一下
hold on a second
我暂停，修正一下
let me pause and fix something
我回来了，抱歉
I'm back sorry about that
不知道这个截图是怎么消失的，但它没了
I don't know how this screenshot disappeared but it disappeared
好的，现在回来了
all right it's back now
你可以打印出当前一直传递的环境变量
so you can print out the environment variables that you currently are passing around
进程在启动别的进程时，传递给对方的环境变量
process pass these environment variables to each other as they execute each other
比如，shell会将它们传给你执行的命令
so your shell will pass them on to any commands you execute
你可以用env命令，查看环境变量
you can check the environment variables you're currently logging around with the env command
这是一个非常有用的命令
it's a very useful command
你应该研究一下它的man手册
and you should study its manpage
特别是在这个模块中
especially for this module
总之，你能用env查看当前设置的环境变量
but you can use env to look at the environment variables that are set
在这个截图中，有一些设置好的环境变量
so in this screenshot I have a bunch of environment variables set
当然，你还可以更新修改环境变量
and then of course you can update your environment variables
比如，使用一些shell语法
by using some shell syntax for example
或者，若不在shell中，可用其它api
or through other APIs if you're not in a shell
比如你在写一个程序
for example you're writing a program
现在环境变量变了
and now my environment variables are different
比如我能修改PATH环境变量
so I can actually for example change the path environment variable
让shell去另一个目录找cat
to make it search for cat in a different place
回到路径
back to paths
若想知道shell会在哪里找到给定程序
if you curious about where your shell will actually find a given program
最终会执行哪个二进制文件
what actual binary will end up being executed
可以使用which命令
you can use the which command
which会找遍你的PATH变量
which searches through your path and returns the
会找遍你的PATH环境变量
searches through your path environment variable
并返回它找到的路径
and returns the file system path of the command wherever it finds it
我们更深入地了解一下文件本身
let's look deeper at files themselves
关于文件我们已经讨论了很多，文件这，文件那
we've been talking a lot about files files files this and that
但我们还没有真正深入研究什么是文件
but we haven't really dug into what a file is right
原来有许多不同类型的文件
it turns out there are many different types of files
我们熟悉的常规意义的文件
the regular concept of a file that you're used to
比如这几个例子中一直在cat输出的flag文件
the flag file you've been catting out in all of these examples that has data
这只是一种类型的文件
that's just one type of files
最常见的就是这种普通文件
the most common one is the normal regular file
你可以用ls -ld命令检查文件
you can use the ls -ld command to look at your files
实际上是ls -l输出了这种长的文件细节数据
really it's ls -l is what gives this long form output of details about files
-d能让你查看目录的数据
-d allows you to also look at directories
通常，ls会查看目录内部文件
normally ls will look inside directories
但用了-d，它就会看这个目录本身
with dash d it'll instead look at directories
所以
so ls -ld
如果我们看一下内有flag的
if we look at the topsecret file that actually has our flag in it
截图中输出的TOPSECRET
that we've been catting out in these screenshots
能看到它就是这种文件
you can see it's the type of the file
这一行第一个字符是 -
the first character printed on the line is a dash
如果你看一下包含它的目录
if you look at the directory containing it
则是d
that is a D
d代表目录
of course d stands for directory
目录实际上是一种文件
directory is actually a type of file
只是它里面记录了其它文件的条目
that just happens to have entries that refer to other files
重申一下，- 代表普通文件
again a dash is just a regular file
还有很多其他类型的文件
there are a lot of other files
有符号链接，一会儿会讲到
there are symbolic links we'll talk about them in next
有有名管道
there are named pipes
我们稍后再讨论它们
we'll talk about them a little later
还有一些奇特的东西
and then there's exotic stuff
比如，字符设备文件
like character device file
这些文件代表硬件设备
these are files that represent a hardware device
通常是硬件设备
usually a hardware device
但也有些操作系统的支持文件
but any sort of device backed by the operating system itself
当然，也会与硬件通信
which of course mediates communication with hardware as well
这里的数据流
that streams data
比如麦克风，对吧
such as a microphone right
块设备是一种加载和存储数据块的设备
a block device is a device that loads and stores chunks of data
比如，硬盘
like a hard drive
还有s，这也是一个奇特的装置（Unix套接字）
and then there's s which is an exotic device
这是Unix中的一种联网方式
that's a way to do networking in Unix
它不需要实际的网络地址
without actual network addresses through these files
这门课我们不用管它
we won't worry about that really in this class
但有趣的是
but as a fun fact
pwn学院的大部分基础设施
much of the infrastructure of pwn College
都依赖这些Unix套接字，以及它们的通信能力
depends on these crazy Unix sockets and the abilities communicate with them
这些是不同类型的文件
so these are our different types of files
我们看看符号链接
let's look at symbolic links
符号链接也被称为软链接
a symbolic link is also known as a soft link
它基本上是一种引用，指向其它文件
it's basically a type of file that references another file
它就像转发地址
it's like a forwarding address
当你尝试打开一个符号链接
you try to open a symbolic link
它会说，不不不，你想要的不是我
and says no no not me not me
是我指向的这个文件
I'm actually pointing to this other file right
用ln命令创建链接时
you create them with the ln command for links
加上-s符号链接参数
link with -s symbolic argument
读一下ln的帮助文档
read the man page of ln
它很有用，有很多好东西
it's very useful there's a lot of good stuff
你可以创建一个文件
and you can create a file
这儿我们创建了符号链接link_to_the_flag
so here we're creating this symbolic link link_to_the_flag
这是一个符号链接文件
this is a symbolic link file
你能看到这个 l
you can see this l
它指向
that points to
我们在当前目录执行ls -l，能看到
when we do ls -l on the current directory
它指向flags/topsecret
points to flags/topsecret
这个相对路径
this relative path
当我们用cat输出这个文件
and then when we cat out this file
我们实际输出的是它的终点
what we're actually catting out is its destination
就是它所引用的文件
it's the file it's referencing
也可以链接到目录
you can also link directories
方法一样
same way
你只需要建立一个链接
you just make a link
能看到
we can look at it
它指向flags目录
and it points to flags
我们可以执行 cat 链接/TOPSECRET
we can cat out the that linked directory slashtopsecret
然后得到了flag
and we get our flag
链接非常有用
links are super useful
原因有很多
they're useful for many reasons and
以至于我想不出一个具体例子
they're so useful that I'm drawing a blank on an example
但如果你在为一个项目构建目录结构
but if you're setting up a development file system
你想引入不同的项目依赖
and you want to link in different repositories
方法a可能不好做
a you're probably doing it wrong
但方法b，你可以用软连接实现
but b you can use symbolic links for that
还有很多其他的东西
and many other things
讲一些符号链接问题
some symbolic link gotchas
符号链接的一个怪的行为是
a crazy behavior of symbolic links is
如果软链接指向一个相对路径
if you have a symbolic link pointing to a relative path
那这个相对路径是相对于软链接的
that relative path is relative to the symbolic link itself
而不是你此时的工作目录
not to your current directory
这里我在/home/yans创建了一个软连接
so here I create a symbolic link in home yans
它指向flags/TOPSECRET
that is pointing to flags topsecret
如果我把它移到tmp中
but if I move that symbolic link somewhere to tmp
再cat输出它
and then I try to cat it out
它实际上会去找/tmp/flags/TOPSECRET
what is actually trying to get at is tmp flags topsecret
虽然我当前的工作目录还在/home/yans
even though my current directory is still in my home directory
当然，它找不到那个文件
and of course it can't find that file
但它的错误提示不会
but rather than print
默认情况，cat打开无效软链接时
by default cat tries to open that file
会直接返回一个错误：文件不存在
and just gets an error that that file doesn't exist
它不会调查它指向哪里等等
it doesn't investigate where it's pointing to etc etc
它会直接告诉你这个链接文件不存在
it just tells you that this link does not exist
这真的很令人困惑，因为这个链接确实存在
which is really confusing because that link very much exists
它就在那里
because it's right here
只是它指向的目标文件不存在
it's just its destination doesn't exist
所以用相对路径时要小心
so be careful about relative paths
这种错误提示的不透明
and this sort of error opacity
提示说符号链接的错误
where you will see errors about the symbolic link
但实际是符号链接目标的错误
but they're really about the destination of the symbolic link
当然，如果你坚持用绝对路径
of course if you just stick to absolute paths
事情往往会好得多
things tend to work much better
但你可能会
but then you might actually
绝对路径有时不是你想用的
this might not be the desired behavior
例如，如果你把/home/yans改成/home/blah
for example if you just rename /home/yans to /home/blah
这个相对路径仍然能用
this would still work with this relative path
但绝对路径就用不了了
but absolute path would then not work
所以取决于你的使用需求
so it depends on your use case
可能会有些问题
there's some gotchas all right
软链接的存在意味着有硬链接
the existence of soft links implies the existence of hard links
它们确实存在
and they do exist
它们是用ln 不加-s参数创建的
they are created with ln without the dash s argument
它们完美地引用了原始文件指向的数据
and they are a perfect reference to the data pointed by the original file
用的和原始文件相同的方法
in the same way that the original file is
实际上，你可以将普通文件视为指向其内容的硬链接
actually you could view any normal file as a hard link to the contents
创建一个硬链接只是多加了一个
and creating a hard link just adds another one right
在这里，当我链接hard_link_to_flag到flags/TOPSECRET
in this case when I link hard_link_to_flag to point to flags/topsecret
这个文件，很难判断它是不是原始文件
that is a file that is very hard to tell that it is not the original file
它们共享相同的内容
they share the same content
如果我修改一个，另一个也会改变，等等
if I modify one the other one will change etc etc
虽然软连接也这样，但硬链接
soft links are that same way but hard links
硬链接与原始文件的路径没有关系
that hard link has no relationship with the original path of the original file
只与数据有关
just with the data
不像软链接
unlike a soft link
如果你对它的原理感兴趣
if you are really interested in how this works
这节课中，我不会详细讲inode是什么等等
I'm not going to go into inodes what they are and etc etc in this lecture
但如果你对它的原理感兴趣
but if you're interested in how this works
你可以深入研究这篇文章，能获得很多信息
you can dig into this post and get a lot of information
我们转到管道
let's move on to pipes
管道是另一种类型的文件
pipes are another type of file
p类型文件，表示有名管道
a p file it represents a named pipe
但在你使用Linux时，计算机上的大多数管道
but most pipes on your computer when you're using Linux
实际上是无名的
actually not named
它们是暂时的单向通道
they are ephemeral channels of unidirectional
在管道一侧写入信息
information where one side of the pipe writes to it
另一边读出信息
and the other side reads to it
这有一个例子
this is an example
如果我cat输出flag
if I cat out the flag
然后计算它的md5值
and I try to compute MD5 sum of it
我输出flag
I can cat the flag out
把它放到管道
I can pipe it
用md5sum计算输入值
I can md5sum that input
所以这个会流入到md5sum
so this flows input into md5sum
同样的，我可以将输入流到shell脚本或shell中
in the same way I can flow input into a shell script or into a shell
我展示一下
let me show you
我们看看这是否可行
let's see if this will work
我展示一下效果
let me show you how this will go
好的，可以
all right this kind of works
我可以执行echo echo hi
I can do echo echo hi
这将输出echo hi
so this will output echo hi
如果我把它用管道输给bash
if I pipe that into a bash shell
bash会执行它
it'll actually execute it
因为bash是shell解释器
because bash is my shell interpreter
它从输入中读取命令
that reads commands from its input
我现在把它作为输入
which I am now making as its input
echo echo hi的输出，即echo hi
the output of echo echo hi which is echo hi
好吧，疯狂的东西
all right crazy stuff
在这个模块中你要非常熟悉它
you'll have to get very familiar with it in this module
这里还只是个预告
but that was a sneak peek
有名管道，因为他们的行为，也被称为fifo
named pipes also known as FIFOs for their behavior
叫做先进先出
it's called first in first out
收到的第一个数据就是输出的第一个数据
so the first data that's received is the first data that's output
后面的数据排到后面
later data goes next and so on
它们是存在于文件系统上的文件
they are a file that exists on the file system that
作用与无名管道相同
acts the same as a pipe
它是个单向的信息流通道
it's a unidirectional channel for information flow
你们也要熟悉这些
and you will have to get familiar with those as well
还有mkfifo命令的使用
and with the mkfifo command
多读man手册
read the man page
我们讨论一下输入和输出重定向
let's talk about input and output redirection
我刚刚很轻松的将一个命令的输出
I very casually redirected output from one command
用管道输入给了另一个命令
into the input of another command with a pipe
但你也可以重定向文件
but you can also redirect files
它的语法基本就是
and the syntax to do so is just tacking on
基本就是<，用于重定向输入
basically a less than for redirecting to the input
> 用于重定向输出
or a greater than for redirecting output to the command itself
可以把另一个文件重定向成输入
I can redirect the input from a different file
把输出重定向到另一个文件
I can redirect output into a file
可以将输出追加到一个文件
I can append output to a file
可以重定向程序的错误输出
I can redirect errors printed by the program
当然，程序会恰当地输出这些错误
course the programs to be care properly print these errors and so forth
但我能用2>把错误输出重定向了
but I can redirect errors written in a program with this 2 greater than syntax
你必须理解
you will have to understand
你需要查阅文档
and you would have to look up documentation
找到这个2>是什么意思
and find why that 2 greater than is a 2 greater than in the course of this module
这基本上就能让你重定向程序的输入和输出
and this allows you basically to redirect input and output of your program
这对脚本、自动化等非常重要
which is super important for scripting automating and etc
好的
alright
这就是我为你们准备的命令行速成课
that is the crash course that I have for you about the command line
如果这是很多新信息
if this was a lot of new information
我强烈推荐
I highly recommend that good cat
我强烈建议你上网查找相关资料
I highly recommend that you look online for resources
以便快速上手命令行
to get up to speed with using the command line
网上有很多教程
there's a lot a lot of tutorials all over the place
比如在YouTube，文档，?挑战系列等等
on YouTube、documentation、？、 challenge series etc etc etc
都能帮你熟悉命令行
on getting very familiar with the command line
本模块需要你熟悉它
you will need it for this module
后面的课程也需要
and you will need it for the rest of the class
这也是为什么有这个模块
and that is why this module exists
在本模块中后面的内容
through the rest of the module
我们将讨论Linux中的程序是如何工作的
we'll talk about how programs work in Linux
如何启动的
how they start up
如何与系统交互的
how they interact with an environment
如何关闭的
how they shut down
这也会帮助你在任务中获得高分
that as well will help you out in your quest to get the top of the scoreboard
祝你好运
good luck